RAMSEY NJEMA JR.

P.O. Box 415 | Zomba, Malawi

Tel: +265 994 574 030 / +265 881 228 002 | Email: rnjema@unima.ac.mw LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/rnjema | Github: https://github.com/rnjema-unima

PERSONAL SUMMARY

Ramsey is a self-driven and budding academic researcher who has been actively involved in developing high-impact digital initiatives using the DHIS2 platform. He has significantly contributed to developing and operationalizing iCHIS, a digitalized nationwide community health services solution, and NAMIS, the national agricultural management information system. In addition to his passion for digital transformation initiatives, Ramsey's research interests lie at the intersection of digital security, AI, and edge computing. Currently, he serves as a staff associate in the Department of Computing at the University of Malawi – where he has been actively involved in teaching, outreach activities, and software development. He firmly believes in community-driven digital transformation, as evidenced by his engagement with Zindi in his role as country ambassador, where he seeks to democratize the knowledge of AI. In addition, Ramsey is an avid enthusiast of emerging technologies such as blockchain, IoT, quantum computing, and GenAI, just to name a few.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

UNIVERSITY OF MALAWI (Department of Computing) Staff Associate/Assistant Lecturer

Part-Time Instructor

Zomba, Malawi June/2023 – Present August/2022 – May/2023

- Teach and prepare assessments for undergraduate modules in Computer Networking and other modules as assigned
 - Assisted in teaching modules such as machine learning, cryptography, and network programming
- Supervise undergraduate student projects

UNIVERSITY OF MALAWI (Department of Computing) **Software Developer/Implementer** (HISP UNIMA)

Zomba, Malawi May/2022 – Present

- Support the development and implementation of a nationwide Communication Health Information System aimed at integrated digitally-supported service delivery by community health workers
- Led the digitalization of a nationwide ITN mass campaign a Malaria prevention initiative

PARTNERS IN HEALTH / ABWENZI PA ZA UMOYO Medical Informatics Intern

Neno, Malawi

August/2020 - October/2020

- Worked closely with the M&E team in ensuring timely, complete, and high-quality COVID reporting, which included fieldwork
- Wrote and designed scripts for automated data retrieval from OpenMRS and DHIS2 that significantly sped up custom report generation.

EDUCATION

UNIVERSITY OF MALAWI Computer Network Engineering (BSc.)

Zomba, Malawi July/2017 – April/2022

Awards

• Deans' List x 2

Projects

• Smart Home Automation System

April 2022

This IoT-based smart home automation system provides a platform for intelligent and efficient consumption of domestic utilities. This was submitted in partial fulfillment for the award of a Bachelor of Science degree and was conducted as a 2-man team effort. My involvement included developing a Flutter mobile app-based user interface and integrating the Firebase backend with the Arduino microcontroller hosting different sensors.

Link: https://github.com/rnjema/smart-home-automation-project

SKILLS

- Mobile & Web Programming Flutter, JavaScript, ReactJS, PHP Laravel
- Databases SQL, NoSQL
- Data Science & Machine Learning Python, Pytorch
- Network Systems Administration UNIX
- Fundamental Network Programming & Applications Development Python, C

INTERESTS & EXTRA-CURRICULAR ACTIVITIES

DHIS2 Tracker Configuration Academy

11th – 15th November 2024

Malawi

Expert Facilitator/Trainer

Malawi

Community Ambassador Country Ambassador September 2022 – November 2024 December 2024 - Present

December

African Drone and Data Academy

Malawi University of Science & Technology

Remote Pilot License Training

January – February 2024

AMLD Africa Ambassador

Zindi Africa

Swiss Federal Institute of Technology in Lausanne (EPFL), Switzerland

September – December 2022

Data Science Africa

Institute of Accountancy Arusha, Tanzania

Participant

 $18^{th} - 22^{nd}$ July 2022

Zindi UmojaHack Africa (Africa's top Inter-University ML Hackathon)

University of Malawi

University Organizer & Participant

March 2022

Malawi Data Science Bootcamp

Mzuzu University

Participant

October/2021 – November 2021

Python Coding Club

University of Malawi January 2022 – Present

Founding Member

University of Malawi

Electronics Student Society

2019 – April 2022

Member

University of Malawi

Member

August 2017 – April 2022

Old Mutual Mathematics Olympiad

Computer Science Student Society

3rd Place Candidate (overall)

Mzuzu University January 2015

Student Debate Club

Pius XII Minor Seminary

President

June 2014 – June 2015